Guide to the Time Inc. Video Group Records 1934-1989 MS 3009-RG 41
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Video Group Records
1934-1989
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 41
112.55 Linear feet in 112 records cartons and 3 flat boxes
The Video Group Records contain materials documenting Time Inc.'s work in the cable, film, and television industries. The Video Group oversaw the departments and subsidiaries that worked directly in these industries. Included in this record group are materials created by the staff of Time-Life Films, Time-Life Video, Time-Life Broadcast/Time-Life Broadcast Inc., Time-Life Cable, Home Box Office (HBO), and Manhattan Cable Television (MCTV).
Historical Note
The first evidence of Time Inc.'s Video Group can be found in 1961. At this time, Weston C. Pullen Jr. was appointed as the in charge of radio, television and real estate within the corporate group. Serving under Pullen were Frederick S. Gilbert, Andrew J. Murtha, Ole G. Morby, and Peter S. Hopkins. Gilbert served as the radio and television general manager, Murtha was the radio and television business manager, Morby was the radio and television assistant, and Hopkins was the real estate assistant. By the next year, this group had disappeared off the department heads list and had been replaced by the Broadcasting division which was not part of the corporate group. All of the employees who had been previously listed under radio, television and real estate division of the corporate group, except for Hopkins, had moved over to this new division. This division continued to be known as Broadcasting until 1968 when it became Time-Life Broadcast.
Time-Life Broadcast continued to function as its own division but in 1970 Time Inc. reorganized so that executive vice presidents oversaw various divisions within the company. When this change took place, Rhett Austell was given the responsibility to oversee Time-Life Books, Time-Life Broadcast, Time-Life Films, Time-Life Records, and Book and Art Associates. By 1972, the divisions that Austell oversaw changed a bit. He now oversaw Time-Life Books, Time-Life Cable, Time-Life Films, Time-Life Records, Time-Life Video, Books and Arts Associates, Book Find/Seven Arts Society Inc, Little Brown and Company Inc., New York Graphic Society Ltd., and Haverhill's.
Between 1972 and 1978, a variety of divisions had come and gone from this yet unnamed group. The biggest change that happened during this period was that divisions related to books and videos had been divided up into their own groups. Divisions related to books were put into the Books Group under group vice president Joan D. Manley and divisions related to video were included in the Video group under vice president J. Richard Munro. In 1978, the Video Group included Home Box Office, Manhattan Cable Television, Time-Life Films, and WOTV – Grand Rapids. While the first evidence for the formation of a dedicated Video Group can be found in the department heads list in 1978, records show the group may have formed as early as 1975. Beginning in 1975, Munro is identified in correspondence as the group vice president of television and films. Since Munro becomes the vice president in charge of the Video Group when it is formed, Television and Films group could have been the precursor to the Video Group.
By 1985, the Video Group had become a shell of its former state. While the group still existed, the vice president of the Video Group mainly oversaw the division heads of Home Box Office, ATC, and Time-Life Video. The Video Group vice president was not involved with the day to day operations of these divisions and the individual divisions were not considered members of the Video Group.
In 1987, the Video Group is no longer listed in the department heads list. ATC and HBO are now listed as their own departments within the department heads lists. Other divisions, such as Time-Life Video, now known as Time-Life Home Video, are part of the Book Group. Prior to joining the Book Group, Time-Life Video mainly worked on movie and television co-productions. Many of these co-productions had been overseen by Time-Life Film but Time-Life Video took over many of them in the 1980 when there was a staff reorganization. After being moved to the Book Group, Time-Life Video slowly shifted away from movies and television. Eventually they became a video subscription service.
Citations:
Personnel and Organization: Department Head Lists. Time Inc. Reference Files (MS 3009-RG 3), New-York Historical Society.
Scope and Contents
The Video Group Records contain materials documenting Time Inc.'s work in the cable, film, and television industries. The Video Group oversaw the work of the departments and subsidiaries that worked directly in these industries. While each department overseen by the Video Group had separate staff and functions, much of their work overlapped, and employees moved between each department regularly. The materials within this record group mainly document the financial relationships and production efforts of each department. Additionally, the Morrie Roizman Files contain scripts and audio reels from the attempted relaunch of March of Time.
Arrangement
This record group is arranged into eleven series:
Series I. Group Vice President of Television and Films J. Richard Munro: Computer Television Files
Series II. Video Group Vice President Files
Series III. President of Video Development Peter Gross
Series IV. Managing Director of New Business Development Susan Ferris
Series V. Publishing and Legal Counsel E. Gabriel Perle Files
Series VI. HBO Records
Series VII. Time-Life Films Records
Series VIII. Time-Life Video Records
Series IX. Time-Life Broadcast/Time-Life Broadcast Inc. Records
Series X. American Television and Communication Corporations: Three Rivers Cablevision Proposal to the City of Pittsburgh
Series XI. Community Antenna Television/Sterling Communications Inc. Files.
Custodial History
Gift of Time Inc. 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials may include contracts and correspondence with personally identifying information. Restricted boxes include R29 through R37 and R57 through R63. Unreformatted audiovisual and digital material in the collection is not accessible. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library. Additional records about the Video Group and information regarding its history can be found in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1). The Time Inc. Book Group Records (MS 3009-RG 28) may also have materials related to work done by members of the video group since the two groups coordinated on special projects.
Agendas; Coproduction (Motion pictures, television, etc.); Corporation records; Corporations -- History; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Correspondence.; cue sheets; Drafts (documents); Film negatives; Financial records.; Invoices; Minutes (administrative records); Notes; Organization files; Press kits.; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Reports.; scripts (documents); Technical reports; Television -- Production and direction.; Television -- Transmitters and transmission.; Television broadcasting; Video recordings--Production and direction; Baily, Mel; Britt, Glenn; Chertok, Harvey; Dolan, Charles F.; Ferris, Susan; Granger, Haidee; Gross, Peter; Lehman, Chris; Levin, Gerald M.; Munro, J. Richard; Osborne, Charles; Perle, E. Gabriel; Roizman, Morrie; Schilling, Richard; Smith, Edgar P., 1920-1989; Time, inc. -- Archives; Time, inc. -- History; Zorthian, Barry, 1920-2010
- Series I. Group Vice President of Television and Films J. Richard Munro: Computer Television Files, 1972-1976; 2.5 Linear feet in 3 records cartons
  Biographical Note
  J. Richard "Dick" Munro began his career with Time Inc. in 1957. After holding other titles, he was named deputy to the group vice president for television and films in 1972, becoming vice president of the group shortly after. In 1978, when the television and films group formally became the Video Group, Munro remained as vice president but left this position in 1980. During the time that Munro served as vice president, he oversaw a project involving Computer Television, also known as CTI, a Time Inc. subsidiary. This project was mainly focused on installing interactive television systems into hotel rooms. Munro and CTI worked closely with the Hilton Corporation to install and test this new system. While Munro left the Video Group, he remained with Time Inc. and became executive vice president of the organization. At the same time that Munro became executive vice president, he also joined Time Inc.'s board of directors. In 1982, Munro was promoted to board president and Time Inc.'s chief executive officer. After Time Inc.'s merger with Warner Communications, Munro maintained his position within Time Inc. but retired in 1990.
  Scope and Contents
  The Group Vice President of Television and Films J. Richard Munro: Computer Television Files cover the period of 1972 to 1976. The materials found in this series focus on finances and operation of Computer Television, a Time Inc. subsidiary which is often called CTI. Included in this series are statement of operations, agreements, Hilton Corporation and CTI reports, agreement overviews, feasibility studies, notes, financial statements, five year plan analysis, budget estimates, preliminary budget estimates and notes, budget reports, meeting agendas, meeting minutes, stock purchase agreements, clippings, travel itinerary, purchase proposals, weekly reports, reports on equipment investigations, personnel and organizational policies, United States labor charges against employer reports, press releases, and correspondence. The correspondence included in this series discuss CTI financing proposals, contracts, financing, medical expenses, company expenses, board meetings, employee contracts, purchase proposals, reports on CTI use, system issues, reports on the use of CTI in Hilton versus other hotels, upgrading room access, promotional materials, agreements, proposed financial plans, liquidation and sale of CTI, board meetings, system test results, monthly operating reports, project updates, negotiations, letters to board and shareholders on interest their interest to sell or acquire assets, project updates, system upgrades, revenue influences, and salaries.
  Arrangement
  Organized alphabetically with general files at the front.
  - General, 1972-1976 (Offsite-box 3340, Folder 1-4)
  - General [RESTRICTED], 1972-1975 (Offsite-box R37)
  - Board Meeting: 1974 November 19 (Offsite-box 3340, Folder 5)
  - Board Meetings, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 3340, Folder 6-11)
  - Board Meetings [RESTRICTED], 1972-1975 (Offsite-box R37)
  - Budget, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 3340, Folder 12)
  - Budget [RESTRICTED], 1975 (Offsite-box R37)
  - Data Architects, 1974 (Offsite-box 3340, Folder 13)
  - Digital Communications, Inc., 1973 (Offsite-box 3340, Folder 14)
  - Expansion, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 3340, Folder 15)
  - Financial, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 3340, Folder 16-18)
  - Furst, Austin: Memos, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 3340, Folder 19)
  - Hilton, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 1-3)
  - Hilton [RESTRICTED], 1974-1975 (Offsite-box R37)
  - Klein, Paul, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 4-6)
  - Klein, Paul [RESTRICTED], 1974-1975 (Offsite-box R37)
  - Magnavox, 1973 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 7)
  - Monthly Reports, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 8-10)
  - Newark Test, 1974 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 11)
  - News Enterprises, 1975 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 12)
  - Paramount, 1975 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 13)
  - Personnel, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 14)
  - Personnel [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R37)
  - Press Clippings, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 15)
  - Rogers Cable TV: Canada, 1975 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 16)
  - Sheraton, 1975 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 17)
  - Sheraton [RESTRICTED], 1975 (Offsite-box R37)
  - Shepley, James: Bi-Weekly Reports, 1973 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 18)
  - Spectradyne, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 19-20)
  - Spectradyne [RESTRICTED], 1975-1976 (Offsite-box R37)
  - Stock Option Agreements [RESTRICTED], 1975 (Offsite-box R37)
  - Time Inc. Financing, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 21)
  - Time Inc. Financing [RESTRICTED], 1973-1974 (Offsite-box R37)
  - Trans World, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 22)
  - Trans World [RESTRICTED], 1974 (Offsite-box R37)
  - Weekly Reports, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 23-24)
- Series II.A. Video Group Vice President J. Richard Munro: Subject Files, 1972-1989; 225088; 3.7 Linear feet in 7 records cartons
  J. Richard "Dick" Munro began his career with Time Inc. in 1957. After holding other titles, he was named deputy to the group vice president for television and films in 1972, becoming vice president of the group shortly after. In 1978, when the television and films group formally became the Video Group, Munro remained as vice president but left this position in 1980. While Munro left the Video Group, he remained with Time Inc. and became executive vice president of the organization. At the same time that Munro became executive vice president, he also joined Time Inc.'s board of directors. In 1982, Munro was promoted to board president and Time Inc.'s chief executive officer. After Time Inc.'s merger with Warner Communications, Munro maintained his position within Time Inc. but retired in 1990.
  Scope and Contents Note
  The Group Vice President J. Richard Munro: Subject files cover the period of 1972 to 1989 and focus on the finances and operations of the Video Group and the companies within it. While this series contains materials from after Munro left the Video Group and became board president and CEO of Time Inc., the majority of materials are from 1977 to 1979 when he was vice president of the Video Group. Included in this series are annual reports, press releases, draft shareholders letters, lists of proposed questions, ordinances, notes, draft letters, cable television reports, clippings, agreement riders, interview question drafts, operating budget reports, American Television and Communications (ATC) annual reports, financial reports, partial copies of securities exchange commission amendments, project overviews, organizational charts, press kits, pay television subscriber reports, five-year plans, activity reports, operating reports, status reports, business report summaries, wage guidelines, cablevision magazine issues, planning worksheets, financial reports, meeting reports, ambassador roundtable programs, forum for world affairs pamphlets, list of meeting attendees, draft speeches, budget re-estimates, balance sheets, budget statements, income statement, Home Box Office (HBO) patches, North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) petitions, telecommunications policy studies, travel schedules, notes, press releases, board minutes, list of board members, board agendas, market estimate reports, intermission programming test reports, Hong Kong Television chairman's reports, notice for shareholders, balance sheets, personnel compensation reports, financial estimates, short range plan reports, personnel cards, and correspondence. The correspondence included in this series discuss advertising contracts, college courses, television show premieres, filmstrips, company transfers, local ordinances, franchises, agreements, project proposals, project plans and objectives, trips, budgets, background research, board meetings, status reports, wages, mergers, purchase proposals, speeches, monthly reports, preliminary budgets versus three-year plans, budget re-estimates, project analysis, wireless mic tests, incentive programs, Home Box Office (HBO) survey analysis, consulting services, profits, business consolidation, new cable services, viewing patterns, marketing, subscriber demographics, and possible television shows.
  Arrangement Note
  Organized alphabetically.
  - America's Black Forum, 1978; 225134 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 25)
  - Annual reports: 1980-1985, 1983-1986; 225133 (Offsite-box 3341, Folder 26)
  - Annual reports: 1980-1985, 1980-1982 (Offsite-box 3342, Folder 1)
  - Annual reports: 1988: Draft letter, undated; 225132 (Offsite-box 3342, Folder 2)
  - Ascent of Man filmstrips, 1975; 225131 (Offsite-box 3342, Folder 3)
  - ATC (American Television and Communications Corporation), 1977-1979; 225130 (Offsite-box 3342, Folder 4-18)
  - ATC (American Television and Communications Corporation) [RESTRICTED], 1977-1979 (Offsite-box R37)
  - BAA - General Learning Corp., 1973-1974; 225129 (Offsite-box 3343, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence/Memoranda: re speeches: 1987-1988, 1986-1989; 225128 (Offsite-box 3343, Folder 2-3)
  - HBO (Home Box Office), 1972-1978; 225126 (Offsite-box 3343, Folder 4-12)
  - HBO (Home Box Office) [RESTRICTED], 1973 (Offsite-box R57)
  - HBO: Board Meetings, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 3343, Folder 13-14)
  - HBO: Board Memoranda, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 3343, Folder 15)
  - HBO: Board of Directors, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 3343, Folder 16)
  - HBO: Board of Directors [RESTRICTED], 1973 (Offsite-box R57)
  - HBO: Budgets, 1973 (Offsite-box 3343, Folder 17)
  - HBO: Financial Statements, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 3343, Folder 18)
  - HBO: Financing, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 3343, Folder 19-21)
  - HBO: Financing [RESTRICTED], 1973 (Offsite-box R57)
  - HBO: Monthly Reports, 1975 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 1)
  - HBO: Three Year Plan, 1973 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 2)
  - HBO: Trendex, 1974-1976 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 3)
  - Hiland Associates, 1977; 225101 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 4)
  - Hong Kong [RESTRICTED], 1975 (Offsite-box R57)
  - Hong Kong: 1977 November 15-22, 225113 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 5)
  - Hong Kong: 1977 November 15-22 [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R57)
  - Hong Kong Television, 1975-1980; 225114 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 6-8)
  - Inland Container, 1978-1980; 225112 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 9-11)
  - Kas Kalba, 1977; 225111 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 12)
  - Life Goes to War, 1977; 225100 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 13)
  - Little, Brown & Co., 1978-1979; 225110 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 14-15)
  - Monty Python series, 1976; 225109 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 16)
  - NBC People Show: Time-Life Films, 1975-1977; 225093 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 17)
  - NBC People Show: Time-Life Films [RESTRICTED], 1976 (Offsite-box R57)
  - "On Our Own", 1977; 225099 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 18)
  - People TV show, 1978; 225094 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 19)
  - Spectradyne, Inc., 1978; 225108 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 20)
  - Talent Associates: Suskind, David, 1977; 225107 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 21)
  - Telemation Program Services, 1976-1977; 225104 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 22)
  - Teleprompter: Home Box Office, 1975-1977; 225106 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 23)
  - Teleprompter: Home Box Office [RESTRICTED], 1975 (Offsite-box R57)
  - Time-Life Films Inc.: Board meeting, 1978-1979; 225103 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 24-25)
  - Time-Life Films Inc.: Bonus plans, 1977-1978; 225102 (Offsite-box 3344, Folder 26-28)
  - Time-Life Films: Financials, 1974-1979; 225097 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 1)
  - Time-Life Films: Home Box Office, 1976-1977; 225098 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 2)
  - Time-Life Films: Meeting: Lyford Cay/Nassau: May 1978, undated; 225096 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 3)
  - Time-Life Films: Personnel, 1972-1977; 225092 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 4)
  - Time-Life Films: Personnel [RESTRICTED], 1972-1975 (Offsite-box R57)
  - Time-Life Films Music Company, 1977; 225095 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 5)
  - United Artists Corp., 1976; 225091 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 6)
  - Viacom International Inc., 1976-1978; 225090 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 7)
  - Western Union proposal, 1975; 225089 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 8)
- Series II.B. Video Group Vice President Gerald Levin Files, 1979-1983; 2.3 Linear feet in 4 records cartons
  Gerald Levin began working at Time Inc. in 1972 when he was hired as vice president of programing at Home Box Office (HBO) which was a premium subscription cable channel. In 1974, he was promoted to chairman of HBO and remained in this position until 1980 when he left HBO to work as vice president of Time Inc.'s Video Group. Levin returned to HBO as chairman in 1982. While resuming his previous position at HBO, he did not leave the Video Group and remained the group vice president. Between 1982 and 1983, Levin continued to serve as HBO chairman and Video Group vice president but left both of these positions in 1984 when he joined Time Inc.'s board of directors and became vice president of strategic planning at the corporate level.
  Citations:
  Lewis, Mark. "Levin's Legacy At AOL Time Warner." Forbes. Forbes Magazine, June 6, 2013. https://www.forbes.com/2002/05/17/0517levin.html#6f13ad7d43bb.
  Personnel and Organization: Department Head Lists. Time Inc. Reference Files (MS 3009-RG 3), New-York Historical Society.
  Vice President Gerald Levin Files cover the period of 1979 to 1983 and focus on the finances and operations of the Video Group and the companies within it. While Levin mainly served as Video Group vice president during this period, he also served as Home Box Office (HBO) chairman from 1974 to 1979 and 1982 to 1983. Since the majority of materials focus on his work as Video Group vice president, these materials have their own series rather than being included with his HBO-focused materials. Included in this series are special equities investment reports, memoranda on the sale of WOTV stations, financial statements, re-estimate reports, financial reports, Grand Rapids Broadcast Division and Time-Life Broadcast financial reports, press releases, agreements, revenue reports, balance sheets, event booklets, legal filings, clippings, press kits, annual securities reports on American Family Corporation, reports on retirement income plans, Time-Life Broadcast strategic plans, WOTV transmitter review reports, Time-Life Films budgets, TV Cable Week reports, issues of TV Cable Week, lists of presentation attendees, magazine prototypes, outlines of acquisition deals, presentation pamphlets, lists of employee contracts, clippings, profit and loss statements, non-theatric market reports, presentation outlines, Search for Alexander the Great scripts, and correspondence. The correspondence included in this series discuss bonuses, appropriations, the sale and purchase of WOTV, finances, revenue, sales, national cable convention, budgets, project pitch, new acquisitions, contract modification proposals, contract terminations, five-year plans, monthly and weekly activity updates, operating incomes, project overviews, project reviews, and distribution plan.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - BBC (British Broadcasting Corporation), 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 9-10)
  - BBC (British Broadcasting Corporation) [RESTRICTED], 1979-1980 (Offsite-box R57)
  - "Fort Apache, The Bronx": Lawsuit, 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 11)
  - Television Cable Magazine, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 12-13)
  - Television Cable Week: STV, 1983 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 14)
  - Time-Life Films, 1980-1982 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 15-17)
  - Time-Life Films: Employee Agreements, 1981 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 18)
  - Time-Life Films: Executive Employment Agreements [RESTRICTED], 1980 (Offsite-box R57)
  - Time-Life Films: Financial Statements, 1979-1981 (Offsite-box 3345, Folder 19-20)